Guide to the Margaret Taylor Smith Papers, 1918-2010 and undated, bulk 1980-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret Taylor Smith papers 1918-2010 and undated bulk 1980-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Margaret Taylor
19.85 linear feet Extent: 24,761 Items
A native of Roanoke Rapids, North Carolina, Margaret Taylor Smith attended Duke University from 1943-1947. After graduating with a degree in sociology, Smith and her husband relocated to Birmingham, Michigan. Smith raised four children while taking an active part in her community through volunteer work and leadership. Smith's work as a research associate studying family life became the basis for a 1987 book, Mother, I Have Something to Tell You. Smith served as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations. In addition, Smith continues her commitment to Duke University by holding leadership positions on multiple boards, by acting as a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies, and by enabling the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies. The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers contain materials dating from 1918 to 2010, with the bulk dating between 1980 and 2008. The collection documents Smith's voluntarism, leadership, and philanthropic activities at Duke University, especially in women's studies; her sociological research on American families, specifically relationships between mothers and children, that resulted in the publication of a book, Mother I Have Something To Tell You; her social and family life; and her professional activities and voluntarism, particularly at the Kresge Foundation. The collection is organized into five series: Duke University, Mother, I Have Something To Tell You, Personal Papers, Professional Voluntarism, and Additions.
RL.01226
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, audio and video recordings in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008, 2010.
Biographical Note
A native of Roanoke Rapids, North Carolina, Margaret Taylor Smith attended Duke University from 1943-1947. After graduating with a degree in Sociology, Smith and her husband relocated to Birmingham, Michigan. Smith raised four children while taking an active part in her community through volunteer work and leadership. Smith was instrumental in founding the Legal Aid Society to provide legal assistance for low income citizens, and New Horizons, Inc. to provide service to individuals with disabilities. She held leadership roles in the Girl Scouts and the Junior League and participated in organizations designed to support children. Smith worked as a research associate at the Merrill-Palmer Institute of Wayne State University, studying family life and early childhood development. Her research became the basis for a 1987 book, Mother, I Have Something to Tell You. Smith served as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations. In addition, Smith continues her commitment to Duke University by holding leadership positions on multiple boards, by acting as a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies, and by enabling the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies.
Collection Overview
The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers contain materials dating from 1918 to 2010, with the bulk dating between 1980 and 2008. The collection documents Smith's voluntarism, leadership, and philanthropic activities at Duke University, especially in women's studies; her sociological research that resulted in the publication of a book; her social and family life; and her professional activities and voluntarism, particularly at the Kresge Foundation. Smith's original folder titles were retained. Smith, an avid note taker, often recorded information on the exterior of folders and manila envelopes. These folders were retained and appear in the collection. The collection is organized into five series: Duke University, Mother, I Have Something To Tell You, Personal Papers, Professional Voluntarism, and Additions.
The Duke University Series comprises materials related to Smith's leadership and professional voluntarism at the university, including correspondence, event planning notes, meeting minutes, endowment information, and speeches.
The Mother, I Have Something To Tell You Series documents the publication of the 1987 book, authored by Jo Brans, based on Smith's sociological research that describes how mothers deal with children who display untraditional behavior. Specifically, Smith researched American families whose children challenged social and sexual mores during the 1960s and 1970s. The series contains correspondence, drafts, speeches, and Smith's research related to the book, including the mothers' subject files, which typically contain written transcripts of Smith's interviews with the women, both with and without Smith's notes, questionnaires and sociological data, and audiocassette recordings of the interviews. Original audio recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.
Materials related to Smith's social and family life are located in the Personal Papers Series, which primarily comprises correspondence with family, friends, and some professional associates, but also includes photographs, newspaper clippings, ephemera from Smith's days as an undergraduate at Duke University, and her father's World War I diary.
The Professional Voluntarism Series contains materials documenting Smith's professional activities, including awards, correspondence, speaking engagements, subject files, voluntarism, and philanthropy. The series particularly highlights Smith's work as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations; her volunteer work with the Junior League; and her interest in ethics and ethical dilemmas.
Later Additions have not been processed. Accession (2010-0066) contains email correspondence. Accession (2010-0135) includes addition research materials, correspondence, proposals, and other miscellaneous notes. Accession (2010-0164) includes correspondence regarding the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; the Duke University Women's Studies department; Smith's Class of 1947 and their reunions; and other miscellaneous materials and notes.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Brans, Jo; Diaries; Duke University -- Alumni; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Women's Studies Program -- History; Junior League of Birmingham, Michigan; Kresge Foundation; Mothers -- United States -- Psychology; Mothers and daughters; Mothers and sons; O'Barr, Jean; Parenting -- United States; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Photographs; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Smith, Margaret Taylor; Voluntarism -- United States; Volunteers and voluntarism -- Women; Women -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Women sociologists -- United States; Women's studies -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives
Contents of Collection
- Duke University Series, 1970-2008 and undated, (7 boxes)
  As a highly involved Duke undergraduate, Smith served as president of Woman's College student government while excelling in scholarship (Phi Beta Kappa), athletics (Delta Phi Rho Alpha), and in leadership (Phi Kappa Delta, White Duchy, Pi Beta Phi). After earning a degree in Sociology in 1947, Smith continued her commitment to the university through leadership, volunteering, and philanthropy. Smith served on the Executive Committee for Duke's Capital Campaign Fund drive, on the Board of Directors of the General Alumni Association, as a member and chair of Trinity College's Board of Visitors, and on the Board of Directors and Executive Committee of Duke's National Council. Particularly interested in women's issues, Smith was a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies and served as president of the Women's Alumnae Association. Smith's generosity enabled the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies. The series also documents the relationship between Smith and Jean O'Barr, who established the Women's Studies Program. Personal correspondence between the two women appears in the Personal Papers Series. The alphabetically arranged Duke University Series comprises materials related to Smith's leadership and professional voluntarism at the university, including correspondence, event planning notes, meeting minutes, endowment information, and speeches. Materials documenting Smith's experiences as an undergraduate at Duke and her social activities related to the university can be found in the Personal Papers Series.
  - Alumni Association Distinguished Alumni Award, 1996 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Awards, Duke Heritage Society and Half Century Club, 1991; 1998
  - Board of Visitors capital campaign, 1990-2000 (4 folders)
  - Council on Women's Studies, 1989-1992 (2 folders)
  - Dinner to honor Mary Grace Wilson, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Elly Elliott honorary degree, 2002 May 10
  - Evaluation of women's studies program, 1990
  - Ford Foundation, 1987-1988
  - Ford Motor Company and Women's Studies correspondence/outcomes, 1990-1991 (4 folders)
  - Founder's Day, Duke University Chapel, 2001 October 4 (2 folders)
  - Fundraising chapter and manuscript of Jean O'Barr, 1992
  - Giving to Duke, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Gratitude for leadership of Council on Women's Studies, 1991 April 15
  - Happer, Carolyn, Duke interview, 2003
  - Hillsdale College inauguration, 2000
  - Jenkins, Kimberly correspondence, 2002
  - Kellogg grant, 1993
  - Margaret Taylor Smith endowed directorship, 1996-1998 (5 folders)
  - Miscellaneous, 2000
  - O'Barr honorary degree, Indiana University, 2002 May 4 (Box 4)
  - Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund, 1991-1995
  - Trinity Board of Visitors, last meeting, 2000 April
  - Trinity Board of Visitors lists, 1988-1995
  - What Makes Sense is That Things Don't Make Sense: Life's Continuing Dilemma, 1987 November 12
  - Woman's College at Duke celebration, 2002 November 8-10 (3 folders)
  - Women and Power, correspondence, 2001
  - Women Imagine Change, 2000 May 4-5
  - The Women's Center, 2004
  - The Women's Center, Donna Lisker, 2003
  - Women's health care, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Women's initiative correspondence, 2003
  - Women's Studies, 1986-2008 (folders 1-6 of 9)
  - Women's Studies, 1986-2008 (folders 7-9 of 9) (Box 6)
  - Women's Studies, correspondence, brochures, and programs, 2001-2003 (2 folders)
  - Women's Studies Council leadership, 2002 (2 folders)
  - Women's Studies external review, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Women's Studies fundraising, 1990
- Mother, I Have Something to Tell You Series, 1981-2007 and undated, (15 boxes)
  In the early 1980s, Smith worked as a research associate at the Merrill-Palmer Institute of Wayne State University, studying family life and early childhood development. Smith collaborated with writer Jo Brans to publish the book Mother, I Have Something To Tell You in 1987. Based on interviews with mothers in Michigan, the book describes how parents deal with children who display untraditional behavior. Specifically, Smith researched families whose children challenged social and sexual mores during the 1960s and 1970s. The series contains correspondence, drafts, speeches, and Smith's sociological research related to the book, in addition to files on each mother, who appeared in the book under aliases provided by Brans. In keeping with the anonymity provided by the book, file names reflect aliases rather than real names. The mothers' subject files include written transcripts of Smith's interviews with the women, both with and without Smith's notes, questionnaires and sociological data, and audiocassette recordings of the interviews. Arrangement is alphabetical, followed by a large group of research files organized into rough book chapters by Smith.
  Original audio recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.
  - Articles in support of project, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
  - Author questionnaire, 1986
  - Biographical data, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Book project notes, 1981-1982
  - Book proposal, 1984
  - Book proposal and Jo Brans notes, undated (Box 8)
  - Book tour and Doubleday correspondence, 1987
  - Contract information, 1984-1987
  - Correspondence, 1981-1987; 2007 (3 folders)
  - Draft, Chapter 1, 1985 April 11
  - Ego level assignments, 1983
  - File from Jo Brans, 1984-1987 and undated
  - Focal child notes, undated
  - Forms and summaries, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
  - Initial correspondence with Jo Brans, 1984
  - Letters to mothers and article, 1985-1986
  - Margaret Taylor Smith story transcription, 1981
  - Master list, 1986-1987
  - My mothers, 1982 and undated
  - Packet for Jo, 1985
  - Project idea development, undated
  - Project origins, 1981 and undated (2 folders)
  - Publicity and correspondence, 1987-1997 (2 folders)
  - Questionnaire for mother, undated
  - Rough draft, process, and outline, 1983-1984
  - Rough drafts, thesis, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Sentence completion tests, undated
  - Speaking engagements, 1987-1988
  - Speaking engagements, Good Day Show videocassette, Boston, 1987 February 2
  - Speaking engagements, WBZ radio show audiocassette, Boston, 1987 January 20
  - Subject 10, Rosemary, 1981-1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 11, Janet, 1982 (folders 1-2 of 4)
  - Subject 11, Janet, 1982 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 11)
  - Subject 12, Carolyn, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 13, Betty, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 14, Ruthanne, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 15, Carol, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Subject 16, Lois, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 17, Bonnie, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 18, Dorothy, 1982-1983 (folders 1-2 of 4)
  - Subject 18, Dorothy, 1982-1983 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 13)
  - Subject 19, Jean, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 20, Kate, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 21, Myra, 1982-1983; 1992 (folders 1-2 of 4)
  - Subject 21, Myra, 1982-1983; 1992 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 14)
  - Subject 22, Rebecca, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 23, Suzanne, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 24, Patricia, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 25, Judy, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subject 26, Marilyn, 1982 (3 folders)
  - Subject 27, Margot, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 28, Susan, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 29, Patty, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Subject 30, Marian, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 31, Margaret, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 32, Ann, 1982-1983 (folders 1-3 of 4)
  - Subject 32, Ann, 1982-1983 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 17)
  - Subject 33, Sharon, 1982 (4 folders)
  - Subject 34, Ellen, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 35, Lucy, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 36, Karen, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Subject 37, Marie, 1982-1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 38, Martha, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 39, Elizabeth, 1983 (folders 1-3 of 4)
  - Subject 39, Elizabeth, 1983 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 19)
  - Subject 41, Gloria, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Subject 42, Joy, 1983 (4 folders)
  - Talk, with various dilemmas and several conclusions, undated
  - Thoughts on readings, 1985
  - Worksheets used for editing, undated
  - Other materials (Box 20-21)
- Personal Papers Series, 1918-2008 and undated, (7 boxes)
  Contains materials documenting Smith's social and family life, primarily through correspondence with family, friends, and some professional associates, but also through photographs, newspaper clippings, ephemera from Smith's days as an undergraduate at Duke University, and her father's World War I diary. Materials related to Smith's volunteer and philanthropic activities at Duke University are located in the Duke University Series. The Personal Papers Series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - 50th class reunion (Duke), 1997 Sept. (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - 60th high school reunion, Roanoke Rapids, 2003 Oct.
  - Clippings and notices, 1942-1946
  - Correspondence, 1994-2000 July (7 folders)
    The correspondence folder for 1994-1998 contains an image of Jean O'Barr with Hilary Clinton.
  - Correspondence, 2000 July-2002 Dec. (7 folders) (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 2003 Jan.-2004 Sept. (7 folders) (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 2004 Sept.-2006 July (7 folders) (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 2006 Aug.-2008 January (3 folders) (Box 26)
  - Clippings from Mary Lou Connolly's scrapbook, 1956-1966 and undated
  - Cramer, Laura house party, Hilton Head Island, 2004 Oct.
  - Cuba, Duke alumni trip, 2003 February
  - Duke clippings, 1940s
  - Duke correspondence, 1943-1947
  - Duke memories, 1940s (folders 1-2 of 4)
  - Duke memories, 1940s (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 27)
  - Engagement and wedding, 1947
  - Journal, 1994 Apr.-Aug.
  - Memories...Conversations with Sarah Waller Taylor and Bertie Waller Brown, 1981 Oct.
  - Mother, 1984-1985
  - My friends, oral conversations, 50th reunion, 1992; 1997
  - Photographs
    - Christening, 2003
    - Digital prints, 2003
    - Duke photographs, 1940s; 1960s
    - Miscellaneous, undated
    - Montreat, North Carolina and T. J.'s, 2003 May
    - My desk, undated
    - Pictures from refrigerator door, 2002-2003
    - San Miguel, Roanoke Rapids, and Cape Hatteras, 2003
    - Sicily, 2001 Oct.-Nov.
  - Picnic, Orchard Lake Country Club, 1984 June 3 (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Sid's 50th, 1999
  - Taylor genealogy, undated
  - Taylor, Sergeant George N. diary, 1918 May-1919 Mar.
- Professional Voluntarism, 1962-2007 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Series houses materials documenting Smith's professional activities, including awards, correspondence, speaking engagements, subject files, voluntarism, and philanthropy. The items give particular emphasis to Smith's work as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations; her volunteer work with the Junior League; and her interest in ethics and ethical dilemmas. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  [Original recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.]
  - Athena Award, 1998 Mar. (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Awards and memorial garden correspondence, 1996, 1999, 2007
  - Correspondence and other writings, 1994-2008 (2 folders)
  - Council of Michigan Foundations, 1992-1997
  - Detroit Medical Center corporate responsibility, 1997-1999 (Box 29)
  - Detroit Medical Center, Hutzel Hospital, 1984-1997
  - Dilemmas, 1986-1988 and undated
  - The Economic Impact of Women in Philanthropy, 1994 Oct. 20 (3 folders)
  - Ethics and dilemmas, 1987-1988 and undated
  - Gender equity reports, 1988-1994 (folders 1-3 of 4)
  - Gender equity reports, 1988-1994 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 30)
  - Health care talk, 1993 Feb. 12
  - Heart of Gold Award, 1985-1987 (2 folders)
  - Human development, 1986-1987 and undated
  - Human risk and solitude, 1987 and undated
  - Junior League Community Advisory Committee, 1998-2000 (2 folders)
  - Junior League, 1987-1989 and undated
  - Junior League presidency, 1962-1964
  - Kresge Foundation
    - Agendas and correspondence, 1993-1994
    - Annual reports, 1994-1998 (2 folders)
  - Kresge Foundation (Box 31)
    - Correspondence and remarks, 1990-1995; 2005
    - Council of Michigan Foundations, 1993-1997
    - Crain's Detroit Business, Detroit's Most Influential Women, 1997-1998
    - New Direction, undated
    - Retirement, 1997 June
    - Trustee-emeriti dinner, 1996 May 16
  - Merrill-Palmer, 1974-1978; 1987
  - Merrill-Palmer directories, 1978; 1980
  - Panel - Class, gender, and race in the non-profit sector, 1996 Jan. 16
  - Parenting and child care, 1986-1988 and undated
  - Philanthropy, 1998
  - Quotes, 1986-1987 and undated
  - Remarks about the Kresge Foundation, P.E.O. meeting, 1997 Apr. 7
  - Speaking engagements, 1986-1988
  - Speeches and remarks, 1987-1988 and undated (Box 32)
  - Talks and information - Legal and ethical responsibilities of trustees and others, 1995-1996
  - Volunteering, Junior League, 1971 and undated
  - Volunteerism, 1986-1990 (2 folders)
  - Volunteerism and philanthropy, 1995-1996
  - Wayne State University School of Medicine commencement luncheon, Distinguished Service Award, 1999 June 8
  - Women of Achievement and Courage Award, 1999 (2 folders)
  - Women and philanthropy, 1989-1996 (2 folders)
  - Women working and volunteering, 1980-1983
  - Women's Educational Equity Act study on gifted women, 1992
  - Women's special connection and communication, 1987 and undated
- Accessions (2010-0066) and (2010-0135), 1981-1985, 2010, (1 box)
  - Projects and correspondence, 1983-1985, 2010 (Box 33)
    Chiefly correspondence (Accession 2010-0135) from 1981-1985 regarding the Fox-Smith Project, conducted at Wayne State University, that studied the pain and stess of women associated with the non-traditional behavior of children. Also includes email correspondence (Accession 2010-0066) from 2010.
  - Letters to benefactors regarding the publication of research, 1985
  - Proposal for book publisher, 1981-1982
    Correspondence and outlines for proposed research and writing projects; outlines for steps of interviewing.
  - Research and correspondence, 1982-1983 (2 folders)
    Includes grant proposals, research proposals, correspondence, and notes on research.
  - Pat Johnson's research, 1983
  - Transcriptions of interviews, 1983
  - Profiles for Focal Children, 1983
  - Accession 2010-0066, email correspondence, 2010
- Accession (2010-0164), 1970-2009, (1 box)
  Acc. (2010-0164) (100 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 1970-2009) includes correspondence regarding the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; the Duke University Women's Studies department; Smith's Class of 1947 and their reunions; and other miscellaneous materials and notes.
  - Duke Reunions Correspondence (Class of 1947), 1970-1997 (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Detroit Medical Center notes, 1997
  - Women's Health and Wellness Weekend, Duke University, October 2007
  - General correspondence, 2008-2009
  - Women's Studies Department, Duke University (correspondence, notes, newsletters), 2008-2009 (2 folders)
  - Jean O'Barr (correspondence, retirement), 2009
  - What Does It Mean to be an Educated Women?, Sallie Bingham Center symposium, (correspondence, printed materials, plans), 2009
- Accession (2011-0077), 1982-2000, (1 box)
  Additional material from Margaret Taylor Smith's interviews, research, and correspondence about Mother, I Have Something to Tell You. Also includes copies of some of Smith's talks.
  - Mother, I Have Something to Tell You (Box 35)
    - 3 cassette tapes
    - Agreements and other materials, 1982-1983